Okay, today's דף daf is כ"ג, Chaf Gimmel, 23, and it's back
to somewhat of a normal size. And we pick up with where
the גמרא Gemara says, איתיבי. Esvei. So if you remember, the issue
here is whether we say the principle of מין במינו min b'mino
when it comes to issues of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Right, there's
a whole question as I mentioned why we had the huge תוספות
Tosafos before
about when do we say this, when don't we say this, different
parameters, כשרות kashrus versus טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Anyway, here we're dealing
in the world of טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, where interestingly the issue
for ביטול bittul seems to be a simple case of a majority.
In another fascinating point, normally we go by 60, but that's when
concerns are about taste. And the question is that when something will
something that has lost its state of טומאה tumah because it's a
minority reawaken when it re-encounters something, either the same liquid, the same
material like water and water, or אביי Abaye who resists that seems
to have conceded the point when it encounters something else that is
טמא, tamei, the case of grain and grain. Although אביי's Abaye objections
seem to be more principled objections, which is that once the טומאה
tumah has gone away, it doesn't reawaken, the thing stops existing. At
least the concession אביי Abaye made at the end of yesterday's דף
daf was that he agrees in principle, the question is the circumstances.
Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara is going to continue this discussion and actually
frame it again in an interesting conceptual way and seems to question
the very principle. So let's take a look. איתיבי, Esvei, it is
after the two dots, it's the first word on the line, about
10 lines down, let's see, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 lines
down. Okay, after the dots. איתיבי, Esvei, I'll ask you. אפר כשר
שנתערב באפר מקלה. Eifer kasher shenisarev b'eifer mikleh. So let's say you
have אפר, eifer, the ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, they
are mixed up with just normal like burnt ashes. אפר מקלה Eifer
mikleh means that it's not the, it's, it's not ashes of פרה
אדומה, parah adumah, it's simple, it's just plain ashes. הולכין אחר הרוב,
Holchin achar harov, you go by the majority, לטמא, l'tamei, for טומאה.
tumah. Now you might want to ask the question about whether you
can use them for פרה אדומה, parah adumah, much more importantly. Right,
for interestingly, that's not the discussion here and that's not directly relevant
for us because we want to know about whether טומאה tumah disappears
or doesn't. So here it says that whether if you have the
majority of the standard ashes, then the ashes of the פרה אדומה
parah adumah like they don't exist and if you touch them you
don't become טמא, tamei, this mixture. If the majority is the ashes
of the פרה אדומה parah adumah and you touch it, you do
become טמא. tamei. Now interestingly, the רש"ש, Rashash, who's...
don't they mix it with water or something? It's not mixed? Ah,
excellent.
So you see, Michael, you're so smart. The רש"ש, Rashash, who is
a very late commentator in the back of the גמרא, Gemara, actually,
I forget his whole what his name stands for, but anyway, רב
שמעון Rav Shimon something. Anyway, apparently the story is that he was
a businessman who paid the printer to include his commentary in the
back of the גמרא. Gemara.
But the interesting thing is that he actually is the one that
always asks like very sharp questions. I mean, and you know,
and he actually points out about this, I'll just read you the
line because it's just so, you know, so beautifully stated. He says
like this, he
says,
let me just find it, where am I, at בכורות... Bechoros... hold
on,
I thought it was right here...
hmm, I'm not finding this...
anyway...
oh, here it is, yes. במיעוט בקיאותי, B'miut b'kiusi, with the, you
know, the smallness of my knowledge, you know, of my erudition, I,
that's very, you know, I mean it's inappropriately humble, but anyway, this
is an enormous תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. In the smallness of my
erudition, לא מצאתי שיהא אפר לבד מטמא. lo matzasi sheyehei eifer levad
metamei.
I've never found that the ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah cause
טומאה. tumah. The הלכה halacha is that somebody that sprinkles the ashes
of the פרה אדומה parah adumah becomes טמא, tamei, but not that
it is actually a source of טומאה tumah through contact. וכן אמר
רמב"ם בהקדמתו לספר טהרות. V'chein amar Rambam b'hakdamato l'sefer Taharos. The רמב"ם
Rambam writes a huge introduction in his פירוש המשניות Peirush HaMishnayos to
טהרות, Taharos, שכתב שאפר פרה אדומה כשר שנתערב במי המעיין יטמא בהם.
shekasav she'eifer parah adumah kasher shenisarev b'mei hamayan, yitma bahem. That when,
as Michael said, when they get mixed with the waters of the
wellspring, you become טמא. tamei. וכן ימי חבורו, V'chein yemei cheverov, וצריך
עיון. v'tzarich iyun. He says, I don't understand this. Since when do
the ashes by themselves become טמא? tamei? Anyway, that is what the
גמרא Gemara sounds like and he doesn't have an answer, so at
least we've noted the question. So it says the ashes of the
פרה אדומה parah adumah are mixed with other ashes,
and you go by the majority. Now, ועירובה אפר מקלה הוא לא
מטמא. v'iruba eifer mikleh hu, lo metamei.
So the implication is that if the majority is ashes of, what
do you call it, of just standard ashes, it will not cause
טומאה. tumah. Maybe again you could say what it means is afterwards
you mix those ashes with the waters, with the, you know, with
the wellspring waters. But whatever, putting the רש"ש's Rashash question aside, it's
that you go by the majority. And if the majority is standard
ashes, it does not, it will not be a source of טומאה.
tumah. דאמרת, D'amarta, now what... And if you said טומאה כמאן דאיתא
דמי, tumah keman de'isa dami, that the טומאה's tumah like it is
present, ניהי דבמגע לא מטמא, nehi de'bemaga lo metame, admittedly it won't
cause טומאה tumah through touch, לטמא במשא, letame be'masa, let it cause
טומאה tumah through carrying. Now, this is a really conceptual jump
or reframing that the גמרא Gemara makes where you understand what it's
saying, but it still is a jump from what we said yesterday.
Yesterday we said, the way we framed it yesterday was that after
ביטול, bittul, that it was dormant, right? And then the whole phrase,
it reawakens when it comes in contact with its own species. The
way I described that is the object is there, the water is
there, but its status has been removed. It's no longer טמא. tamei.
Once it becomes back into the majority, the status sort of reasserts
itself as opposed to saying the object goes out of existence. The
גמרא Gemara takes it one step further. Look at the phrase of
the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says, if you think it can
reawaken, says the גמרא, Gemara, what you are saying is טומאה כמאן
דאיתא דמי. tumah keman de'isa dami.
It's like the טומאה tumah is present, not dormant, present. So the
גמרא Gemara is saying that the way the גמרא Gemara understands the
way טומאה tumah wakes up is as if the actual status got
wiped away, then it's like אביי Abaye said, how would it become
reinstated?
So the only thing you could say is that the טומאה tumah
is actually there. It's actually alive and present. So if it's alive
and present, then why aren't you טמא tamei anyway for this? So
the גמרא Gemara says, oh, maybe here's the difference. Maybe all we're
saying is that you can't get to it. That if the majority
is something else, then it's considered like you're touching the other thing.
So if you take a look, think for example about our case
about the brine and the water. So if you want to say
the water can reawaken, it means you're saying it's always there and
there's always טמא tamei water there. Oh, if there's always טמא tamei
water there, so why aren't I טמא tamei when I touch it?
Since the majority is the brine, we say you're touching the brine
and not the water. So therefore if that's the logic then by
the ashes we'll say you're touching the other ashes and not the
ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. גמרא Gemara says fine, but
that's when the issue is touching and there's a question about physically
what are you coming in contact with. But the ashes of פרה
אדומה parah adumah also cause טומאה tumah through being carried. When you're
carrying, you're carrying everything. So if you're carrying everything, why should it
matter whether it's the minority or not? So here the גמרא Gemara
does a major jump from yesterday. It doesn't say, it says in
order to say reawaken, we're not going to be able to say
it's dormant. If it's dormant, then we're going to re-read אביי. Abaye.
If the status was removed, it remains removed. How does it get
reinstated? So the only way we can understand it reawakened is that
we're going to say it's actually present and active but inaccessible. If
that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, at least you should have טומאה
tumah where you don't have to touch it, when you carry it
you should become טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara actually buys into
the assumptions of this question and then is going to try to
argue why that, you know, how to adjust. Let's read the answer
and then I'll take your question, just do the one line answer.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
איתמר עלה, itmar alah, well it was said about this, אמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Chanina, so רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Chanina clarifies, טהור מלטמא במגע אבל מטמא במשא.
tahor militame be'maga aval metame be'masa.
So he says, yeah you're right, you're right, okay, you don't become
טמא tamei through touch but you do become טמא tamei through carrying.
So the גמרא Gemara here now says to say טומאה tumah reawakens
means that we actually say it's always present, you just don't have
access to it. And therefore the only issue is a question of
touch, but if it's a question of carrying you would be טמא.
tamei. And of course we're going to have to go back because
remember one of the cases we dealt with was also about the
fetus, right, the dead human fetus, that's טומאה tumah of a מת,
meis, which is also not about touch, it's just about presence in
the house. So all of those are going to now have to
be addressed if we say that the טומאה tumah remains active. Though,
you had a question.
Yeah, the idea that it's there but it's not accessible because you're
touching the other stuff. Right. When you think about the fish brine,
right, even though the only way that that you can talk about
that case is, you know, it's not you're mixing it all together,
it's נשיקה, neshikah, right, that when you put it in the מקוה?
mikvah?
Oh, well that's when you put it in the מקוה. mikvah. Oh,
no, but the actual case of the brine is that you created
a mixture of fish oil and water.
Okay, but I thought you were going to say something else. I
thought you were going to say, of course you're touching both, it's
not like you have this sheath of fish brine surrounding an inner
piece, you know, an inner content of water. It's all mixed together.
But then we define, we define that since the majority is brine,
we define that what you've touched is the brine because that defines
the majority of the act. But yeah, anyway, yes.
In the case of fish brine, the liquid part of the fish
brine
could,
it's all liquid.
Yeah, so it's going to be difficult to extract from the water
mixture. Right. But the ashes are solid. Right. And at least in
theory you should be able to extract.
Yeah. So, you know, in the laws of כשרות, kashrus, the ראשונים
Rishonim create two conceptual categories. I mean, they're really categories in the
גמרא Gemara but the ראשונים Rishonim frame them as לח בלח lach
be-lach and יבש ביבש, yavesh be-yavesh, liquids mixed with liquids and solids
in solids. And what they're really describing is that whether are we
talking about a full dispersal and you know, or are we talking
about separate units. Now there are things that are physically separate units
but in terms of practically we essentially treat them as
liquid. You could take out each grain but in practice in practice
it's like one unit and
and right so so presumably we're saying the same here right I
mean actually it's interesting you know because one way of defining liquids
is that they they conform to the shape of the container well
if you take I mean each individual piece of flour does not
but if you pour a bunch of flour into a container right
as a as a quantity it takes the shape of the container
ashes is a little different you're right they're not as granular as
the flour but the גמרא Gemara is seeming to treat this as
a type of לח בלח lach belach as a type of you
know one one type of a mass that's mixed together. All right
so that is the גמרא's Gemara now statement there but because we
define it by the majority you don't touch it but it's still
present and that's the only way it can reawaken. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this ואמר רב חסדא Ve'amar Rav Chisda so
let's look about other cases doesn't רב חסדא Rav Chisda say נבילה
בטילה בשחוטה neveilah beteilah bishchutah
if you have a נבילה neveilah getting mixed up in a שחוטה
shechutah in a שחוטה shechutah animal now in שחוטה shechutah meat now
again that really does make you think about separate solid individual unit
although again by the way the גמרא Gemara describes it it sounds
more like you're talking about ground meat that gets mixed up together
hamburger let's now let's see שאי אפשר לנבילה שתעשה שחוטה she'ee efshar
leneveilah shete'aseh shechutah
because a נבילה neveilah cannot be made into a שחוטה. shechutah. Why
is he saying that what does that mean? So first of all
what he's saying is the following is that there's a position in
the גמרא Gemara רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that מין במינו לא בטל.
min bemino lo batel. If two things are the same מין min
they are not בטל. batel. We actually rule like the rabbis that
they are but there is that opinion and he's coming to address
that opinion. So he has to therefore emphasize
that although these are both meat and meat נבילה neveilah and שחוטה
shechutah they're considered separate מינים. minim. Why are they separate מינים? minim?
Because well one is נבילה neveilah and one is שחוטה. shechutah. Well
if you say that means everything is a separate מין min because
that's obviously why you want to do ביטול bitul because one is
kosher one is not kosher. But no there's a limit because here
he says how to define if it's a separate מין min would
mean not just right now they're different but is it possible that
one could somehow transform halachically into the other? So a שחוטה shechutah
can never become a נבילה. neveilah. Now that's clear right something that's
kosher cannot become נבילה neveilah and not kosher. Actually that is רש"י's
Rashi גירסא girsa in the גמרא. Gemara. רש"י's Rashi גירסא girsa in
the גמרא Gemara is שאי אפשר לשחוטה שתעשה נבילה. she'ee efshar lishchutah
shete'aseh neveilah. So since the שחוטה shechutah cannot become a נבילה neveilah
they're separate מינים minim and they can't become בטל. batel. They're considered
separate even within רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda construct this is a take
on רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda construct that מין במינו לא בטל. min
bemino lo batel. However the גירסא girsa of it's impossible for a
נבילה neveilah to become שחוטה shechutah which would also seem
true non-kosher meat doesn't become kosher רש"י Rashi says that's actually not
true because here we're talking about ביטול bitul for the purposes not
of eating but of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah as will become clear
and as is our whole context. And there actually we say that
a נבילה neveilah can be like a שחוטה. shechutah. Why? Something that's
טמא tamei can lose its status of טומאה. tumah. How can it
lose its status of טומאה? tumah? If it becomes completely inedible and
rancid and rot which is what we're going to get to at
the bottom of this דף daf then it actually loses its טומאה.
tumah. So רש"י Rashi actually switches the גירסא girsa then and says
the whole point is to say that there is the one thing
that cannot transform is the is the שחוטה shechutah meat cannot actually
become like a נבילה neveilah and a source of טומאה. tumah. Okay
that's just about that phrase. The basic point though is they're mixed
together and they're בטל batel and now again we're dealing not with
kashrus but with טומאה tumah and therefore the נבילה neveilah loses its
ability to be מטמא metamei once they're mixed together. Now the גמרא
Gemara says like this ונהי דממגע לא מטמא v'nehi d'mimaga lo metamei
I still don't get it. Once we're saying that the טומאה tumah
can reawaken it means that it's still active and just not accessible.
So I'll grant you that you won't become טמא tamei through touch
I can't get it but לתמי במשא l'tamei b'masa become טמא tamei
through carrying it. So the נבילה neveilah and נבילה neveilah causes טומאה
tumah through carrying. So even if it's in this mixture now that
makes it clear that we're dealing with of course well no but
not of for the נבילה. neveilah. That makes it clear that we're
dealing with by the way a hamburger type of mixture because if
we're dealing with solid pieces of meat so while it's true from
a kashrus perspective if I had three pieces of meat two are
kosher and one is not I'm allowed to eat them all because
that's ביטול bitul and it's all dry and whatever but if the
issue here that the גמרא Gemara is saying is that the only
reason you're not טמא tamei that the טומאה tumah remains active and
is only and is saying that the only thing that happens is
it's not accessible well if there's three separate pieces of meat what
do you mean it's not accessible? I'll touch each one and I've
touched it. So since the גמרא Gemara here is granted that the
טומאה tumah remains active and is only and is saying that the
only thing that happens is it's not accessible we have to be
talking about a case of a type of like ground hamburger meat
mixed all together. And since it's hamburger meat mixed all together it's
defined by the majority it's not accessible but it's still present and
active so the גמרא Gemara says become טמא tamei therefore if you
carry it.
That's interesting so if you carry it to your dinner table you're
טמא tamei but you can still eat it. Is that is that
what comes out?
But no every time you eat yes although I'm not that is
a good point which which is we are dealing this whole idea
that it remains active you know and the גמרא Gemara the jump
the גמרא Gemara made from yesterday to today is yesterday it said
it reawakens. Today it said in order for it to be reawakened,
we have to say it's active and it's just not accessible. So
the point is like, are we going to transfer that idea to
כשרות? kashrus? By כשרות, kashrus, there also might be that something reawakens.
I mean תוספות Tosafos is huge, תוספות Tosafos and all the ראשונים
Rishonim say that if like the case I gave you remember yesterday
with the חזיר chazer drip, you know, that was dripping into the
pot, so even though it becomes בטל, batel, once it's tastable, then
it becomes אסור assur again. So would we say, oh, since it's
possible that it'll become אסור assur again once it becomes tastable, even
right now it's present? So if right now it's present, how can
I eat the soup, right? And we do say you can eat
the soup. That's the whole principle of ביטול. bittel. Okay, so clearly
these discussions, the discussion of what we're saying by טומאה tumah has
to be held separate from the discussion of what we're saying by
כשרות. kashrus. And one possibility is, one possible reason is, is that
by כשרות kashrus you need a lot more to affect ביטול. bittel.
By כשרות kashrus you need sixty times to affect ביטול. bittel. So
therefore it's easier to say it goes out of existence. Here, remember,
we're saying ביטול bittel is affected just by majority. So if it's
affected more by majority, the גמרא Gemara is more willing to consider
the idea that it's somehow present but inaccessible, but has not gone
out of existence. So in your case, Michael, I mean you'd have
to, it would depend, majority, sixty, etc. So the answer might be
no, because if he actually mixes it together, then actually you need
sixty and then it's not בטל batel from a כשרות kashrus perspective
either.
Sorry, I mean if there is sixty, then it is בטל batel
from a כשרות kashrus perspective.
But then it's also not present.
In which case it wouldn't be טמא במשא. tamei bemassa. Could be.
If there isn't, then it's only like, you know, רוב. rov. Yeah,
רוב. rov.
Then from a כשרות kashrus perspective it's not בטל batel anyway. Okay,
but then it's טמא. tamei. Exactly. So it is good that, you
know, that is a good contrast, which is, this is a very
bizarre idea that it's not just saying the potential to reawaken, but
saying it's currently active. We certainly don't say that by כשרות. kashrus.
You can eat the soup once a חזיר, chazer, a drop of
חזיר chazer went in, even though it could potentially reawaken. We don't
say it's active. One difference might be כשרות kashrus and טומאה, tumah,
but what makes most sense as the difference is that here we're
talking about majority. And if it's only majority, that explains why the
גמרא Gemara is not willing to say that the complete, the other
thing stops existing or even is neutralized, maybe at most it becomes
inaccessible. So that explains why it's a very limited idea of ביטול
bittel that we're dealing with here. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so in the נבילה neveilah case, why doesn't, why aren't
you טמא tamei by carrying it? So לטמא במשא. letamei bemassa. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
where were we? So it says, אמר ליה, amlei, so he said
to him, אתון דרב חסדא מתניתו לה. atun deRav Chisda masnisu lah.
You teach that in the words of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, and
therefore since רב חסדא Rav Chisda says that as a blanket statement,
it sounds like it's not טמא tamei either way. אנן בדי רבי
חייא מתניתו לה. anan bid'Rabbi Chiya masnisu lah. We have it as
a ברייתא braisa of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, not as an amoraic
statement. תני רבי חייא, tani Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught
as a
ברייתא: braisa: נבילה ושחוטה בטלו זו בזו. neveilah u'shchutah batlu zu bezo.
נבילה neveilah and שחוטה shchutah are בטלו זו בזו, batlu zu bezo,
and on that tannaic statement, ואיתמר עלה, ve'itmar alah, we have a
statement of an אמורא. amora. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא amar Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Chanina who clarifies and says: טמא לטמא במגע ומטמא במשא.
tamei letamei bemaga u'metamei bemassa. Exactly what you wanted to say. Yes,
you're not טמא tamei by touch, but you are טמא tamei by
carrying. So again we are basically conceding the point. If all you
have is ביטול ברוב, bittel berov, then it can reawaken, but that
also means that it's currently active and present and you just can't
touch it. But if you carry it, you are טמא. tamei. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue to ask, getting
back to our
משנה. Mishnah. והתנן, veha tnan, how about our משנה? Mishnah? רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב אומר: Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer: בהמה גסה ששפכה חררת
דם. beheimah gassah sheshafchah hararas dam. A large animal like a bovine
cow, you know, dropped a clot of blood, a clump of blood,
and we assume that that's basically a dead fetus. הרי זה יקבר,
harei zeh yikaver, you bury it,
because you can't get benefit if it's a בכור bechor and so
on. ונפטרה מן הבכורה, venifterah min habechorah, and the animal is exempt
from בכורה, bechorah, the next animal, because this is a fetus and
the next one therefore is not the firstborn. ותני רבי חייא, ve'tani
Rabbi Chiya, and the same רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught,
right, the same רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya we quoted before: אינו מטמא
לא במגע ולא במשא. eino metamei lo bemaga velo bemassa. Here it's
explicit, not through touch or carrying. So why is it that this
thing, which we've basically been assuming is a fetus mixed up with
a lot of other liquids and blood and so on, we, why
is it not טמא tamei through carrying? We thought the reason it
wasn't טמא tamei was because it was בטל. batel. But now you're
saying that the ביטול bittel only works for touching purposes, not for
carrying purposes. אמאי, amai, why is it that carrying you're not
טמא? tamei? ניהי דבמגע לא מטמא, nehi de bemaga lo metamei, admittedly
you're not טמא tamei through touch because of ביטול, bittel, לטמא במשא,
letamei bemassa, be טמא tamei through carrying. אישתיק, ishtik, he was silenced,
he didn't have an answer. פקע, paka, you're right. Sounds like there's
another opinion out there that you're also not טמא tamei through carrying.
Also taught by רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya.
And it's the same רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, right. Although before רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya wasn't clear, it was רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya was
just clarified by רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina who
split between carrying and touching. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya himself didn't say,
didn't say one way or the other. אז דילמא, so dilma, so
now maybe however to clarify whether he came back and said this
or whether, you know, the גמרא Gemara is saying this, anyway דילמא,
dilma, maybe שאני הכא דהויא ליה טומאה סרוחה. shani hacha dehavya leh
tumah sruchah. Really, forget how we explained it two days ago, that
it was because of ביטול. bittel. The reason this thing clump of
blood does not cause טומאה tumah is because the fetus has completely
become rancid and because if the נבלה neveila which is what this
fetus is is completely disgusting and inedible and so on it does
not carry טומאה tumah anymore. Okay and that's the meaning of the
משנה Mishna and not because of ביטול. bitul. So now we're going
to analyze that question about a נבלה neveila becoming rancid does it
cause טומאה. tumah. One minute. הניחא לבר פדא hani nicha leBar Padda
one minute. That works according to בר פדא Bar Padda דאמר טומאה
חמורה עד לגר וטומאה קלה עד לכלב. de'amar tumah chamura ad lager
vetumah kala ad lekelev. בר פדא Bar Padda says that the weighty
טומאה tumah I'm going actually read this תוספות's Tosafos's way not רש"י
Rashi because it just fits better. Anyway תוספות Tosafos says what that
means is something that is like a source of טומאה tumah like
like נבלה neveila that loses its power to be a source of
טומאה tumah once it becomes unfit for human consumption עד לגר ad
lager for a convert because the תורה Torah speaks about or not
convert excuse me the stranger the תורה Torah speaks about feeding a
נבלה neveila to a to the resident alien resident non-Jew so from
there we're going to learn that it's only considered a נבלה neveila
when it is fit to be eaten by a human fit for
human consumption. So for something to have טומאת נבלה tumas neveila to
be a source of טומאה tumah it has to be fit for
human consumption וטומאה קלה vetumah kala a lighter טומאה tumah again I'm
reading this תוספות's Tosafos's way what תוספות Tosafos says this means is
not as a source of טומאה tumah but as a receiver of
טומאה. tumah. So if טומאה tumah touches food right it it it
becomes טמא tamei through contact with a source of טומאה. tumah. That
food will remain טמא tamei even when it's no longer fit for
human consumption but עד לכלב. ad lekelev. It'll be remain טמא tamei
until it is until it is not even fit for the consumption
of dogs for animal consumption okay. So for something to be a
source of טומאה tumah like a נבלה neveila again not everything that's
a source of טומאה tumah things are sources of טומאה tumah because
they're not even considered food like you know whatever a dead body
is a source of טומאה tumah it's nothing to do with it
being food. But something that is a נבלה neveila which is a
type it's a source of טומאה tumah but it's a type of
a thing that like a something that's normally would be considered food
so that because that has to be fit for human consumption to
be able to be טמא tamei as something that receives טומאה tumah
as food it's enough that it remains remains fit for animal consumption
for it to be able when it received the טומאה tumah but
as a source it has to be fit for human consumption. Therefore
says the גמרא Gemara
why is this fetus not a נבלה neveila and doesn't have טומאת
נבלה tumas neveila because in this state it's might dog might eat
it dog might love it it's nice and bloody or whatever but
it's not fit for human consumption. And since it's not fit for
human consumption it has nothing to do with ביטול bitul that's why
it's not the source of טומאה. tumah. So גמרא Gemara says okay
that works according to בר פדא Bar Padda who says that for
נבלה neveila it's about human consumption הא לא חזי לגר ha lo
chazi lager
this isn't fit for the resident alien it's not fit for human
consumption so it's not a source of טומאה. tumah. אלא רבי יוחנן
ela Rabi Yochanan according to רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan דאמר אחת זו
ואחת זו עד לכלב de'amar achas zu ve'achas zu ad lekelev whether
it is a source of טומאה tumah or whether it is food
that received טומאה tumah it has it's enough it remains טמא tamei
as long as it's fit for the consumption of dogs so this
thing is certainly fit for the consumption of dogs הא חזי לכלב.
ha chazi lekelev. This is fit for the consumption of dogs so
you're back to your question. You can't say that it's not fit
for consumption according to רבי יוחנן. Rabi Yochanan. You can't say if
ביטול bitul means that it still is טמא tamei through carrying then
it doesn't explain why our משנה Mishna says it's not טמא tamei
through carrying. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. Alright we don't
have a good explanation. So now we have two ways of reading
the משנה. Mishna. Why is this thing not cause טומאה? tumah? One
is ביטול bitul and then that would mean that ביטול bitul really
means that it stops being טמא tamei altogether not even through carrying.
Now we were okay with that yesterday. Now we're assuming that if
it has the ability to reawaken it means it's still active right
now and it causes טומאה tumah through carrying. So therefore that can't
be the explanation of the משנה Mishna can't be ביטול bitul and
the only thing it could be is because it's not edible for
human consumption which only works according to בר פדא Bar Padda according
to רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan that doesn't do the trick. According to
רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan as long as a dog will eat it
it's still source of טומאה. tumah. Yes.
So
this חרחרת דם charcharas dam so we're saying is ודאי vaday like
fetus? Yes. Because otherwise you could have said like you know say
it's ספק. safek. Right. Say it's ספק safek fetus or not then
say ספק safek female or male then take two ספקות safekos together
and then say it's not a בכור bechor at all and then
say you're
okay.
What? Yeah but that's not the משנה. Mishna. You're not giving an
alternate explanation of the משנה Mishna you're just saying you're going to
פסקן. pasken. Yeah so the גמרא Gemara is assuming ah so you
are right that it is a ספק safek male or female. Right.
Oh so your only question is what therefore why do you bury
it? Meaning meaning this second animal is definitely the second one is
ודאי פטור מבכור vaday patur mibechor because we're saying that this not
ספק safek we're saying this is ודאי vaday fetus. Now your question
of it might be ודאי vaday a fetus but it's not ודאי
vaday a בכור bechor because it might be a female so why
do you bury it? So first of all you could say that
you bury it because it's a ספק. safek. you don't want to
be נהנה. ne'ene.
And the other reason you buried it is what the גמרא Gemara
said is לפרסם lefarsem that the mother's פטור מן
הבכורה
patur
min
habechora that you shouldn't think that this wasn't a fetus.
But you are correct which is that we don't is that we
don't we do consider this to be ודאי vaday a fetus. Could
you have read that there was no because as soon as it
was a ספק sofek fetus then the mother would then the next
child would have been a ספק בכור. sofek bechor. Yeah. So the
גמרא Gemara is assuming that somehow you know. I don't know exactly
how, sort of like the גמרא Gemara before. How do you know
if a miscarriage is a miscarriage? It says you ask an expert
shepherd. Okay. So it's not giving us the it's not giving us
the characteristics to judge when we know this חררה סתם charara stam
is a fetus, but it is assuming that it's a ודאי vaday
fetus. You are correct about that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: גופא. gufa. Yes? Did you conclude that if you
carried this thing you're not טמא tamei even though you don't know
why? Well, the משנה Mishna says, not the משנה, Mishna, excuse me,
the גמרא's Gemara's statement about רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says you're not
טמא tamei when you carry it.
The גמרא Gemara doesn't know why.
There's one possibility is ביטול, bitul, but now we've rejected, yesterday that
was possible, today we're saying ביטול bitul you'll still be טמא tamei
if you carry it. So the only possibility is that it's not
fit for consumption, but that only works according to the opinion that
you go by human consumption. So if you say you go by
animal consumption and ביטול bitul doesn't do the job, then it's hard
then we can't understand רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. Yes. You're just suggesting
the placenta stays as a placenta or a fetus becomes afters in
the placenta? I'm just curious about that. Yeah, I don't know I
don't know the medical answer to that, but the טומאה tumah is
caused by the fetus, not by the placenta. Right. Okay. Yes, so
we are assuming that there's a fetus there. Okay, so let's take
a look back. גופא. gufa. Let's look back at this debate about
whether something has to be fit or not. בר פדא Bar Padda
אמר amar
טומאה חמורה tumah chamura עד לגר
ad lager וטומאה קלה vetumah kala עד לכלב. ad lakelev. A source
of טומאה tumah has to be fit for human consumption.
A lighter טומאה, tumah, meaning it
receives טומאה tumah from something else, it's enough that it be fit
for eating for to be eaten by a dog. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan אמר amar Rabbi Yochanan says אחת זו ואחת זו achat zu
ve'achat zu עד לכלב. ad lakelev. Either way it's enough that it's
fit for a dog. Either way it will still remain טמא tamei
unless it's completely inedible. So מאי טעמא דבר פדא? mai ta'ama deBar
Padda? What's the reasoning of בר פדא? Bar Padda? דכתיב dechativ לא
תאכלו כל נבלה, lo tochelu chol neveila, you shall not eat any
any נבלה, neveila, any corpse of an animal, לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה
ויאכלה, lager asher bish'arecha titnena ve'achala, give it to the stranger or
to the resident alien. הראויה לגר קרויה נבלה, harauya lager keruya neveila,
it's only called a נבלה neveila when it's fit for human consumption,
ושאינה ראויה לגר אינה קרויה נבלה, veshe'eina rauya lager eina keruya neveila,
if not, not. By the way, this is a principle that's used
not only for טומאה tumah but for כשרות kashrut as well, that
when things are inedible they lose their state of being of being,
you know, not kosher. Now the question then becomes, as we'll discuss
in a minute, what if it started with that state and then
lost it? So hold off, we'll talk about that in a minute.
ואידך, ve'idach, what would the other one say back? Isn't it clear
in the פסוק pasuk it has to be fit for human consumption?
למעוטי היכא דהסריחה מעיקרא. lema'utei heicha dehisricha me'ikara. No, that's if it
was never fit for human consumption. If it was never fit for
human consumption, it was never considered a נבלה, neveila, then I admit.
But once it was at one stage fit for human consumption, it
won't lose that state until it becomes unfit even for animal consumption.
ואידך, ve'idach, the other one will say back, הסריחה מעיקרא לא צריכא
קרא למעוטי. hisricha me'ikara lo tzericha kra lema'utei. If it was never
fit for human consumption, you wouldn't need the verse to say that
it's not a נבלה. neveila. עפרא בעלמא הוא, afra be'alma hu, it
starts off being dirt. So obviously if the verse is if you're
using a verse, I would never have thought that something that was
inedible from the beginning would have been considered a type of a
food, a type of a נבלה. neveila. ואידך, ve'idach, the other one
says yes, so therefore the other one says no, maybe I would
have, it's still a נבלה, neveila, you know, certainly maybe for טומאה
tumah purposes and who knows, maybe even for כשרות kashrut purposes. So
therefore that's so that's the question, whether you would have taken whether
you would have known on your own that if it was never
fit for eating that it would have been permitted. So בר פדא
Bar Padda says I would have known that on my own, so
therefore the verse is telling me that even if it started fit
and is now not fit, it's no longer מטמא. metamei. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, I'll only concede the case when it
started unfit. Now by the way, I can this to me is
very important, it's a principle that appears in different forms in הלכה,
halacha, what I call sort of like the I call this the
stickiness principle, which is is that it's got to be there's got
to be a better name for it anyway, which means that once
something has a status, it's harder for it to lose it. Right?
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan concedes that if the animal were never fit
for human consumption, it would not be called נבלה. neveila. But once
it was fit and once it was considered edible and food and
it's given the status of a נבלה, neveila, that status will remain
until it gets completely out of the category of food and until
it becomes even inedible for the consumption of animals. Okay, and that
is a principle that we do find in a number of places,
like if something became became not kosher because טרפה treifa got mixed
up and it was edible, you know, does it how will it
lose that status of being טרפה treifa because there was some טרפה
treifa in the mixture might require getting to a point beyond what
what you know what it would have required to have resisted getting
that status to begin with. Once that status is given, it's harder
to lose. You know, once you get, you know, once it's in
life, once you're labeled a certain way, it's hard, you know, to
change that. That's also true here. And assumptions that are being made
about, you know, that if you defined end of life in a
certain way, you know, then do you define like beginning of life
in the same type of a way. And, you know, it seemed
to me, I thought of an interesting analogy with these types of
discussions that when somebody, you know, already is defined, you know, already
is living and alive and whatever, to, and I think intuitively we
understand this, right? That to say that they are now considered dead
would require maybe getting to a point beyond which, you know, the
end point would not be the same as the beginning point. You
know, once somebody is alive, to say that they're no longer alive
requires maybe more complete loss of faculties, you know, than it would
have said at the beginning point. Anyway, without getting into that, that's
a digression. But the point is, is that it's interesting, this idea.
Staying more on point, the question that Michael was saying before about
חמץ, chametz, right? There's a question about חמץ, chametz, right? Does something
stop being חמץ chametz because it is not fit for human consumption,
or does it have to also not be fit for the consumption
of animals? And it's a similar type of a question. Once something
gets a certain status, right, if it was something never fit for
human consumption, then it's not חמץ. chametz. If it was once fit
for human consumption and now it's not fit, but it's still fit
for animals, then it would retain the status. So it's the same
idea that once something gets a status, it's harder to lose it.
That at least is the position of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says if it started off edible, then it's
going to have to be completely inedible even for dogs in order
for it to lose the status, whereas בר פדא Bar Padda says
even if it started off, even if it started that way, it
will lose the status once it's not fit for human consumption. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues. תנן. Tnan. We taught: רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer, בהמה גסה ששפכה חררת
דם הרי זו תקבר. behema gassa she-shafcha chararat dam harei zo tikkaver.
Okay, so this if a, this if a animal, you know, dropped,
this is basically our משנה, Mishna, right? This clump of blood you
bury it, ונפטרה מן הבכורה, ve-nifterah min ha-bechorah, it's exempt from בכורה.
bechorah. ותני רבי חייא, Ve-tani Rabbi Chiyya, אינה מטמאה לא במגע ולא
במשא. einah metamma lo be-maga ve-lo be-massa. And רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya
said that it's not through, that it won't cause טומאה tumah through
touch or carrying. We've already talked that. ואמר רבי יוחנן משום ביטול
ברוב נגעו בה. Ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum bittul be-rov nag'u bah. It's
because of ביטול ברוב, bittul be-rov, which is just what we were
bothered with a second ago. And then we said how does ביטול
ברוב bittul be-rov address the carrying case, and we had to say,
alright, maybe it's not fit for consumption, etc. But now the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask the question in the reverse. Why do you
need to say ביטול ברוב? bittul be-rov? Just say it's not fit
for eating. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי איריא משום ביטול ברוב?
mai irya mishum bittul be-rov? Who needed that? תיפוק ליה דלא חזיא
כלל. teipok lei de-la chazya klal. It was never fit for eating.
So which is actually exactly what we did say a minute ago.
We were bothered by ביטול, bittul, we gave another answer that it
wasn't fit for eating. But now the גמרא Gemara is saying, well,
maybe it implicitly acknowledges that you needed the ביטול bittul answer if
you said that not fit for human consumption was not a sufficient
explanation, right? So then if it's, if being not fit, if you
still need fit, so therefore we needed the ביטול bittul answer if
we say that even when it's not fit for human, it still
causes טומאה. tumah. But now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, this
piece of blood, this clump of blood was never fit in its
entire life, it never lived or whatever, from the beginning of its
existence was never fit for human consumption. And we just got through
saying that even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan admits that if it wasn't
fit from the outset, it is not the source, he admits that
that case, if it wasn't fit from its very beginning, then it's
not the source of טומאה. tumah. So why does anybody need the
explanation of ביטול ברוב? bittul be-rov? Are people with me here? It's
getting a little complicated, but again, basically you've had two explanations about
this clump of blood. One was ביטול, bittul, the other it wasn't
fit. The wasn't-fitting answer we said only worked if you said it's
sufficient to not be fit for human consumption. So we assume that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who needs it not fit for dogs would
go by the ביטול bittul answer. But now we're saying, one minute,
even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't need the ביטול bittul answer because
this thing from the very beginning wasn't fit for human consumption. Shouldn't
that be enough? So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הא נמי חזיא מעיקרא. ha nami chazya
mei-ikkara. No, this was originally fit for consumption. Why? אגב אימיה. agav
immeh. Via its mother. What the heck does that mean? So it
could mean that, oh, as long as I'm eating the mother, if
I would have שחטed shecht and it was in the mother, I
wouldn't have minded if I came across a piece of clumped-up blood,
I would have eaten that as well, which is what? So it's
also possible to explain that it's not because I would have eaten
it, but since it was part of the mother, it's considered fit.
However, you eat a steak, you don't necessarily eat all the, you
know, all the, right, right. But okay, and therefore you're saying if
it was one unit, then I would have judged it in terms
of the mother. Right. But the other problem is one minute though,
one minute, but we don't really care if it could have been
eaten. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying that it's from the moment
it becomes a נבילה, neveilah, right? If it was, if it was
never fit from the moment it becomes, it should have been a
נבילה, neveilah, it didn't become a נבילה. neveilah. Now this clump of
blood when it was part of its mother wasn't a נבילה. neveilah.
It was only a נבילה neveilah once it was ejected. Well, starting
at that second it wasn't fit, so it never got the status
of נבילה. neveilah. It doesn't matter what it was in the mother,
it never got the status of נבילה. neveilah. So based on this,
some אחרונים acharonim say it seems from this גמרא Gemara that you
have this dead fetus in the mother that actually is already considered
to be a נבילה neveilah within the mother's womb. And then it's
a little bit funny because then you're playing it both ways. Okay,
so for נבילה neveilah you'll say it's already נבילה, neveilah, but to
judge whether it's edible, you'll look at it as a one unit
together with the mother and say that it is edible. So it's
a very bizarre, bizarre is the wrong word, but anyway, it's a
very sort of tightrope type of an answer to try to say
that we're going to join those categories together. Yeah, and that's what
we said is, so in that case it's not בלוע? balua? Right,
so that's the thing is, it's a נבילה neveilah that can't cause,
can't convey its טומאה tumah yet because it's בלוע, balua, but it's
still in terms of the object is a נבילה. neveilah. It doesn't
bother me to say that a dead fetus in the mother's womb
has an independent status and is already a נבילה neveilah even though
the טומאה tumah can't come out. What bothers me is that at
the same time you're saying that it's a נבילה, neveilah, you're also
saying that we're going to consider it to be fit to eat
because it is part of the mother. יליץ Yalitz fit to eat?
I mean, either first of all you wouldn't eat it if you
really שחט shachted the mother, and number two is that how can
you say הלכה halacha conceptually it's a unit with the mother at
the same time saying that it's a נבילה? neveilah? Anyway, that's very
difficult. But that sort of wraps that issue, well no, now we're
going to really wrap it up, but that is the important question
about things losing their status and רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan idea that
it's easier to gain a status than it is to lose it.
Once you have the status, you have to reach a higher threshold,
you have to be completely out of the category to be considered
to have lost it. And what do we hold like in terms
of this? In terms of the טומאה tumah issue, I believe we
actually hold like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Which also has important relevance
like I said, the question is applying that by analogy to כשרות
kashrus or as like the פסח Pesach issue. Let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara now. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over
there, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer, and
this is in מכשירין, Machshirin, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov says ציר טהור, tzir tahor, so he's once again with the
fish brine, שנפלו לתוכו מים כלשהן, shenaflo letocho mayim kolshehen, a little
bit of water fell into it, טמא, tamei, it becomes טמא. tamei.
Why? This is the principle of, you know, that the מצא מין
את מינו וניעור, matza min et mino venior, it wakes up again.
Okay, so water comes in contact with water, it wakes up again.
According to אביי Abaye that says basically rejects that idea, you have
to say the water that fell in was טמא tamei water, so
there he admits that טמא tamei and טמא tamei wakes itself up.
So now now we're getting again this idea that it wakes itself
up. ציר טהור. Tzir tahor. Oh, I'm sorry, so the ציר טהור
tzir tahor is that the what? I'm sorry, there must be some
טומאה. tumah. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, right right right, I didn't explain
it. The ציר טהור tzir tahor is that you took this ציר
tzir of עם הארץ am ha'aretz that had a certain constant of
water and we treat that the water that was added was טמא.
tamei. How did the ציר tzir become טהור? tahor? Because you did
what we taught yesterday, which is you put it in the מקוה.
mikvah. Okay, and which now, that מקוה mikvah will only, won't help
if the majority is ציר. tzir. Because if the majority is ציר,
tzir, since the water's the minority, it's considered like what happened, the
מקוה mikvah thing did not relate to the water because the minority
doesn't have a presence. Okay, although again it's a little ironic because
we just got through saying that even when it's the minority it's
still present and active, just not accessible. You would think that might
help for the מקוה mikvah case as well, but we're saying not,
that the going in the מקוה mikvah didn't help for the water.
So the water remains טמא, tamei, although not accessible and therefore not
a problem. A little water gets added to it and then it
reawakens. Okay, maybe even a little טמא tamei water gets added to
it, it's a question that's the issue of אביי, Abaye, and then
it reawakens. So this is based on what we taught yesterday. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, this tells us, נחשדו עמי הארץ על
עירוב מחצה מים בציר, nechshedu amei ha'aretz al eiruv mechtza mayim batzir,
that basically these עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz, which are the people we're
getting it from, it's why we consider the water טמא, tamei, they
water down their ציר tzir up to fifty percent water. Okay, because
he says if it was not fifty percent, it was forty percent,
a drop of water wouldn't reawaken it. Right, how does one drop
of water bring the water back to the surface and create reawaken
the problem? Because we assume until that point it was just under
the majority and one drop of water tips the scales and makes
it the majority. So you see we have to be concerned that
ממש mamash up to fifty, it could be up to fifty fifty
percent diluted. Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to talk about that in
a minute. ציר Tzir is the brine, the fish brine. Okay, so
you see that. So the גמרא Gemara says ולמה לי מחצה, velama
li mechtza, why do you need to say fifty percent? אפילו בציר
ממחצה, afilu batzir mimechtza, let's say it's forty-nine point nine percent, נמי,
nami, דהאי משהו הוי פלגא, dehai mashehu havei palga, this extra drop
of water makes it exactly fifty percent, ופלגא לא בטיל, upalga lo
batil, and you don't need the water to be the majority, you
just need it not to be nullified. So once if it were
exactly fifty-fifty, no side wins and therefore the water isn't nullified. So
how do you argue fifty percent, it really would have said forty-nine
point nine percent we could have said and then this drop of
water would have made the difference. So the גמרא Gemara said no,
אימא עד מחצה, eima ad mechtza, fine, okay, it means that they
water it down up to up to half, not exactly half, up
just up to a half. And therefore the extra drop of water
will now create a problem. But it's possible that they watered it
down that much that one extra drop will make the difference. אי
בעית אימא, Ei ba'it eima, if you want you could say, טומאת
עם הארץ דרבנן, tumat am ha'aretz derabbanan, first of all the whole
fact that we treat
the... So therefore
since it's only a problem if the water's a majority and we
say that that does happen or could happen when one drop is
added, it shows you that before that drop is added we were
concerned that they dilute it up to fifty percent. Okay, so the
wrap-up of all of this is, bracketing the whole question about things
becoming inedible and do they have to be inedible for human or
for dogs, what we said, the stickiness factor. The major theme here
has been the one about טומאה tumah being mixed up and there's
two points. Number one is that you only need a majority to
say that it's, it loses the טומאה. tumah. On the other hand
you have the possibility of חוזר וניעור chozer v'ne'or reawakens. Abaye seemed
to argue in principle on that but in the end seemed to
only argue about the application. And then the question is how do
we understand it reawakens? Yesterday we were happy to say, well, it's
lying dormant, the status is removed but the status could come back.
But here the גמרא Gemara thinks today that if it reawakens it
means that it's already active just inaccessible, which leads it to say
that through carrying it, it would still be a problem and what
I said is that maybe the reason, normally we don't think ביטול
bitul is so ineffective as just there but not accessible, but maybe
part of it is because the other half is that we're talking
only about a simple majority. And since we're talking only about a
simple majority we're going to say that the thing is really like
present and active and just inaccessible. If it was something like a
normal ביטול bitul like sixty times, there we would say it completely
gets nullified, the object goes out of existence, certainly the status gets
removed, but here we could be talking about a more presence of
this minority because it was only a simple majority that is negating
it. Okay, and then we ended with of course that last case
of a drop of water being added to the mixture and therefore
tipping the scales in the other way. Yes, Charlie.
With the double דרבנן derabbanan why isn't it just simply טהור? tahor?
Because we don't always say that a double... First of all, there's
a question about גזירה לגזירה gezeira l'gezeira which means, and even there
we do, but that means whether we will consciously make a safeguard
to a safeguard, but that's a question about where we legislate. Here
we did not make a safeguard to a safeguard. We said there
are two separate sort of institutions that are present. One is the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz and the other is liquids and they come
therefore it's not like we said, oh this is a safeguard, we're
not going to add this to this. There's טומאת עם הארץ tumat
am ha'aretz that's one דרבנן, derabbanan, there's טומאת משקין tumat mashkin that's
another דרבנן. derabbanan. They're independent. In this case they intersect. We're not
going to stop applying our rabbinic institutions because they got doubled up.
But it does mean because it's a double דרבנן derabbanan that it's
much weaker and therefore we have cases in which we're more lenient.
We could have used this in terms of the עשרת המינין. aseres
haminim.
That is true. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. So that
was certainly a challenging piece but again I found it personally quite
fascinating because I'm half of my time teaching כשרות, kashrus, so the
idea about again that there's a concept of it directly discusses what
happens during ביטול, bitul, is it active or dormant, and how do
you understand it and the difference between maybe a majority ביטול bitul
versus larger ביטול, bitul, to me that is a fascinating question. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara now goes on. משנה. Mishna. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel אומר.
omer. Now we get into something a little more accessible. הלוקח בהמה
מניקה מן העובד כוכבים. halokeach behema menika min ha'oved kochavim.
You buy a nursing animal from a non-Jew. Like this week's פרשה,
parsha, right, גמלים מניקות ובניהם, gemalim menikos uvneihem, right?
So you buy an animal with
the young or you buy both?
Both. Okay. So
you buy it with its young. אין חוששין שמא בנה של אחרת
היה. ein chosheshin shema bna shel acheres haya.
So you're not so concerned, oh well,
maybe it is, well it's not clear, it doesn't matter if you
buy it with its young. You just buy an animal that's lactating.
You are not concerned whether this one actually gave
birth. One minute. Right,
right. You're not concerned that this animal never gave birth,
the fact that it's lactating is maybe it was nursing another animal's
child. No, if it's lactating then we of course assume that it
did give birth and therefore the thing that comes after is a
definite non-בכור bechor and not even a ספק. safek. That's reasonable. That's
essentially the question about חלב, chalav, right, whether lactating exempts or not.
Okay. נכנס לתוך עדרו. nichnas letoch edro. Now let's say you go
into your flock and all you have a lot of animals and
they were all about to give birth and you went in the
next morning and you found that there were a lot of new...
births in your in your barn, okay? And what did you find?
וראה המבכירות מניקות ושאינן מבכירות מניקות. vera'ah hamavkirot menicot veshe'einan mavkirot menicot.
You saw the animals that had never given birth yet and they
were they were nursing young, and the animals that had given birth
in the past were nursing young now. Here, every animal has given
birth, but the question is which one is the בכור? bechor? Is
it possible that one animal is nursing another animal's young? They're swapping
their young. So the point is, which of these newborn babies is
a בכור bechor or not? Can I assume that they're nursing from
their mothers and therefore identify which is a בכור bechor based on
what I know about their mothers? Okay, so it says we are
not concerned. אין חוששין שמא בנה של זו בא אצל זו או
שמא בנה של זו בא אצל זו. ein chosheshin shema bnah shel
zu ba etzel zu o shema bnah shel zu ba etzel zu.
We're not concerned that the the children are nursing from a different
mother, and therefore we say any animal that's nursing is nursing its
own child. So if this animal had not given birth until this
morning, then this child is the בכור. bechor. Now do we know
about this? I actually think that there are cases, right, where animals
that are nursing... Again, the first thing is the simple point. Animals
don't lactate unless they've given birth. That's the question about חלב. chalav.
Okay, as a question.
Actually, they can. What? Given the right hormones, they will.
Ah, so that's so thank you, we were being... we speculated on
that when you weren't here a few days ago, that there could
be hormonal imbalance that will lead to
that, and that's the גמרא Gemara of whether lactating itself is sufficient
evidence. This משנה Mishnah assumes that lactating is sufficient. The possibility that
they would lactate without giving birth is very rare. But if animals
have given birth and are lactating, will they nurse other animals' young?
That I think does actually occur, right? Does it occur pretty frequently
or rarely, do you know?
It doesn't happen very often because usually the mother is there. However,
if the mothers die...
Ah, okay. If the mothers die. But if the mother's there, it
would be very rare, right? Okay, so that's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב נחמן משמיה דרב. amar Rav Nachman mishmeih deRav.
So Rav Nachman says now in the name of Rav, הלכתא ככולי
פירקין. hilchata kechulei pirkin. We rule like all of the משניות Mishnayot
in our פרק, perek, בר מפלוגתא, bar miplugta, except where the issue
is debated. So any statement that was made in the משנה Mishnah
that was not debated, we rule like. Okay, maybe I would have
normally assumed that anyway. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to make
a point though, which is that that statement is redundant because most
cases are debated, and the ones that aren't debated, we would have
known anyway we rule like them. So let's take a look.
אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, אמינא, amina, I said, כי נים
ושכיב רב אמרה להאי שמעתתא. ki nayim veshachiv Rav amrah lehai shma'ateta.
Rav must have been dozing off. What did you say this? Because
אהי, ahi, which case do you... which case is it talking about?
אילימא רישא, eileima reisha, how about the first case? Remember that the
first case was a question about how old the animal is and
can we assume whether it gave birth or not? So that's a
debate.
מפלגי רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא. miflagi Rabbi Yishmael veRabbi Akiva. They debate
whether you have to be concerned about a prior miscarriage or not.
אלא דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. ela deRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. The statement
we just had about רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
which was our whole case about the clump of blood, right? The
fetus. So רבי אליעזר...
so there we always... we know you go by רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov משנת רבי אליעזר בן יעקב קב ונקי.
mishnat Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov kav venaki. We say that the teaching
of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov is like a
קב, kav, like a small measure of grain, but it's very sifted,
it's very clean, which means that רבי אליעזר בן יעקב does not
have too many halakhic positions, but the ones he does say, they're
very solid and we go by them. So we know that we
go by the previous משנה. Mishnah. אלא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. ela
deRabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So it must be our משנה Mishnah about
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel thing about nursing animals.
So מפלג פליגי בברייתא. miflag pligi bebraita. That's not unanimous. We're going
to see a ברייתא braita we're going to quote in a minute
that it is debated. So there that's not a non-debated case. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא אדרבי יוסי בן המשולם. ela adRabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam. So the
משנה Mishnah of רבי יוסי בן המשולם, Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam, which
is coming up, the next משנה, Mishnah, which has to do with
if you have hair that came off of a בכור bechor and
then you שחט shacht the בכור bechor and what's the status of
the hair? That's the next משנה. Mishnah. So that's what you're telling
me. So that's the only משנה Mishnah in our פרק perek which
is not debated and is not self-evident that we rule that way.
So that's what you're telling me. הא אמר רב חד זימנא. ha
amar Rav chad zimna. You already told me that in another way.
דאמר רב הלכתא כרבי יוסי בן המשולם. damar Rav hilchata keRabbi Yossi
ben HaMeshulam. Just you said straight that we rule like him. So
why do you have to make this general statement, oh, we rule
every time there's not a debate? אלא
אשיער בעל מום. ela as'ar ba'al mum. It must be about... I'm
sorry. רבי יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam was prior. רבי
יוסי בן המשולם Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshulam was if you שחט shacht
the בכור... bechor... was the משנה Mishnah about שחיטה shechitah the בכור.
bechor.
And then the next משנה Mishnah was about the hair of a
בעל מום. ba'al mum. So rather... so... okay, what was this? So
דף כ"ד עמוד ב'. daf chaf daled amud bet. רבי יוסי בן
המשולם אומר השוחט את הבכור עושה מקום לקופיץ וכו'. Rabbi Yossi ben
HaMeshulam omer hashochet et habechor oseh makom lekofitz vechulei. Okay, and then
the משנה Mishnah on כ"ה chaf hei is the hair of a
בעל מום, ba'al mum, the hair that fell off.
So רבי אליעזר בן... so... so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi בן המשולם
we know we rule like him. So it must be on the
next משנה Mishnah about the hair of a בעל מום. ba'al mum.
So מפלג פליגי. miflag pligi. עקיבא בן מהללאל ורבנן. Akiva ben Mahalalel
veRabanan. That's debated. So again, the only... The only משנה Mishnah that's
not debated is רבי יוסי בן משולם Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam which
you already told me we rule like him and who was it?
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov that we know we
go by him. So what is the purpose of this statement?
רבא Rava says לעולם le-olam it's רבי שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel. Really it's going on our משנה, Mishnah, which is why
it's being quoted here, on רבי שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel statement. Okay, now, והא קא משמע לן, ve-ha ka mashma lan,
so what it's telling me is דברייתא לא פלוגתא היא. de-braita la
plugta hi. When he said we go like all of our cases
in the משנה Mishnah which are not debated, he means which are
not debated in the משנה. Mishnah. Even though there'll be a debate
in the ברייתא, braita, since it's not debated in the משנה Mishnah
we rule like it. So that you need to tell me because
we're going to see that רבי שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel position is debated and רבא Rava is saying since in the
משנה Mishnah it's not debated we rule like him. Okay, now that
we have another question, if that's true, וכיון דאמר מר הלכה ככולי
פרקין בר מפלוגתא, ve-keivan de-amar mar halacha ke-chulei pirkin bar mi-plugta, if
רבא Rava is saying we go like our whole פרק perek except
where there's a debate, הלכה כרבי יוסי בן משולם למה לי? halacha
ke-Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam lama li? Why did he after also say
we go like רבי יוסי בן משולם, Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam, which
is also stated without a debate? Once you are making this and
now we understand that it's coming to include רבי שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, it also includes רבי יוסי בן משולם, Rabbi
Yossi ben Meshullam, why do you have to tell me that separately?
So אי אמר הלכה ככולי פרקין, ei amar halacha ke-chulei pirkin, if
he had just said we rule in the entire פרק perek on
the positions that aren't debated, ולא אמר הלכה כרבי יוסי בן משולם,
ve-lo amar halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam, and he did not say
that we rule like רבי יוסי בן משולם Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam
in the next משנה, Mishnah, הוי אמינא דרבי יוסי בן משולם קאי,
hava amina de-Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam kai, that that statement we rule
like the פרק perek what things aren't debated is going on רבי
יוסי בן משולם. Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam. ומהי ככולי
פרקין, u-mai ke-chulei pirkin, our entire פרק, perek, if it's only one
statement? So דרבי יוסי תרתי אמר, de-Rabbi Yossi tarti amar,
because we'll see in the next משנה Mishnah רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi,
has two statements. So therefore although it only applies to רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yossi? we say all the times it's not debated, what of
that's the two statements of רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi. That's how I
would have interpreted it and I wouldn't have applied it to רבי
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. Why not? ופלוגתא דברייתא פלוגתא,
u-plugta de-braita plugta,
because there's a debate of רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel of the ברייתא. braita. So I would have said that's a
debated point and that statement only refers to רבי יוסי בן משולם.
Rabbi Yossi ben Meshullam. So אשמעינן הלכה כרבי יוסי, ashmeinan halacha ke-Rabbi
Yossi, so first he had to tell me no, first I want
it to be clear we rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi Once
he says that, what's the... and then he says and we rule
like the סתם משנה, stam Mishnah, it obviously isn't referring to the
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, case, he already told me that. So אשמעינן
הלכה כרבי יוסי לאשמעינן דרבי שמעון בן גמליאל קאי, ashmeinan halacha ke-Rabbi
Yossi le-ashmeinan de-Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel kai,
that when he says we rule like the סתם משנה stam Mishnah
he is not referring to רבי יוסי, he is referring to our
משנה Mishnah רבי שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel. ופלוגתא דברייתא
לא פלוגתא היא, u-plugta de-braita la plugta hi,
and the opposing opinion in the ברייתא braita is not relevant because
it's not an opposing opinion in the משנה. Mishnah. So the upshot
of all of this is that we rule like רבי שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel against what we are going to find
is the opposing position in the ברייתא. braita. Now that we do
have a few minutes and we quoted it let's just get to
the two dots and see the opposing opinion in the ברייתא. braita.
מאי ברייתא? mai braita? What is the opposing opinion? דתניא, de-tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: braita: הלוקח בהמה מניקה מן העובד כוכבים, halokeiach
behemah menika min ha-oved kochavim,
you buy a nursing animal from a non-Jew, הבא אחריה בכור מספק,
ha-ba achareiha bechor mi-safek,
it's a doubtful בכור, bechor, מפני שמרחמת, mipnei she-merachemet, because
it has compassion on other animals' young, אף על פי שאינה יולדת,
af al pi she-eina yoledet, even though it has not given birth.
Now that's amazing that the compassion that it has for the young
causes it to lactate. Now again Dvorah my wife did tell me
that there is some documented evidence that mothers who adopt infants will
begin to lactate. It's also interesting if you think of again the
term מרחמת merachemet of רחם, rechem, right, and the גמרא Gemara maybe
thinking that there is a connection between that feeling, that emotion, and
leading to the ability, the lactating. But that is a... that's a
very big
חידוש, chiddush, that even lactating we might think that maybe it hasn't
given birth, even though it's lactating maybe it hasn't given birth and
it's just doing it because it has adopted this young. So that's
one debate on the משנה. Mishnah. Now we go on. אף על
פי שאינה יולדת. af al pi she-eina yoledet. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר דבר בחזקה, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer davar be-chazakah, that no
it's בחזקתה be-chezkatah that you assume that an animal does not lactate
until it's given birth. וכן היה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, ve-chen
haya Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel also used to say: הנכנס לתוך עדרו בלילה, ha-nichnas le-toch
edro ba-layla, you went into your barn at night, וראה כעשר
כחמש עשרה מבכירות ושאינן מבכירות יולדות, ve-ra'ah ke-eser ke-chamish esreh mivkirot ve-she-einan
mivkirot yoldot, some had never given birth, some had already given birth,
and they were in the process of giving birth, I mean they
were about to give birth. למחר השכים ומצא, le-machar hishkim u-matza, and
then you woke up the next morning and you went into your
barn and you found זכרים תלויים בשאינן מבכירות ונקבות תלויות במבכירות, zecharim
teluyim be-she-einan mivkirot u-nekeivot teluyot be-mivkirot,
you saw that all the males were nursing from the animals that
had given birth in the past, and all the females were nursing
from the animals, the new young, from the animals that had never
given birth. So the upshot will be that no בכור, bechor, right?
אינו חושש שמא בנה של זו בא אצל זו, eino choshesh shema
bnah shel zo ba eitzel zo, you're completely exempt from בכור, bechor,
there's no doubt and that's his position. So there you see it's
debated, but okay the interesting thing is is that we would have
more expected a debate not about the case whether a lactating animals
that had never given birth. So the upshot will be that no
בכור, bechor, right? So אין חושש שמא בנה של זו בא אצל
זו. ein choshesh shema benah shel zu ba etzel zu. You're completely
exempt from בכור, bechor, there's no doubt, and therefore and that's his
position. So there you see it's debated. But okay, the interesting thing
here is that we would have more expected a debate not about
the case whether a lactating animal is a ספק. safek. That we
say, no, if it's lactating it definitely has given birth. We would
have expected the question about, I think I would have, whether maybe
it really has the wrong animal nursing from it and can you
assume based on the animal that's currently nursing is genuinely the child?
So that we have yet to see debate, but that actually makes
more sense to question than the issue about an animal that's lactating
to think maybe it never gave birth. Just want to read I
think what's next and just want to read
an interesting line in תוספות Tosafot of הנכנס Hanichnas why he gave
exactly this scenario of the night before and the next morning. So
if you look at the tiny little תוספות הנכנס, Tosafot Hanichnas, the
middle of it, ויש לומר v'yesh lomar he says like this: דדווקא
נקט הכא
דאף על גב דודאי היתה תחילה לידתה בלילה d'davka nakat hacha d'af
al gav d'vadai hayta techila leidata balaila שעדיין אין האמהות מכירות בוולדותיהן
she'adayin ein ha'imahot makirot bevladoteihen
that maybe they don't even recognize their young so much. I don't
know about animals how much they need to see or how much
it's more hormonal or they know anyway. But the point is don't
think that. So the whole point is don't think that. Don't say,
oh, it was night, maybe they've got the wrong animals got mixed
up. No, ודרכן לינוק זה מזה וזה מזה אפילו הכי לא חיישינן.
vedarkan linok ze mize veze mize afilu hachi lo chashinan. So that's
the point. Even though it was all at night, רבי שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel says we're not concerned. It's nursing the
animal that is its young, you don't have to be concerned it's
another young child. Charlie, you had a question?
So why didn't רב Rav just say הלכתא כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל
hilchata k'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel and
הלכתא hilchata whatever?
Yeah. It's that by saying it as a general point he was
actually saying that that maybe is what maybe he's influenced by the
fact, meaning what's motivating him to say that is the fact that
it's סתם stam and not מפורש. meforash. Of course the question still
is why here as opposed to other chapters, you know. So yeah,
I don't really know unless it was a way easy way to
remember, although given how much the גמרא Gemara had to discuss it
it wasn't such an easy way to remember. Right. Okay.
יישר כוח. yashar koach. Yeah.
We are just trucking.